Theodosius Dobzhansky Papers ca.1917-1975 Mss.B.D65
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, ca.1920-1975; 7.5 linear feet
  - Taylor, Walter K., 1972; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Teachers College Record, 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Teilhard de Chardin Centre for the Future of Man, 1970-1975; 6 folders (Box 14)
    - Folder 1, 1970; 4 items (Box 14)
    - Folder 2, 1970; 9 items (Box 14)
    - Folder 3, 1971; 4 items (Box 14)
    - Folder 4, 1972; 23 items (Box 14)
    - Folder 5, 1973-1974; 11 items (Box 14)
    - Folder 6, 1970; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Templeton, A., 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Terzian, Annette, 1974-1975; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Tewfik, Helmy R., 1970-1972; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Thacker, Franklin P., Jr., 1972; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Thames Television, 1972; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Thimann, Kenneth V., 1973; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Thoday, J. M., 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Thode, Barbary, 1970; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Thoms School, 1969-1970; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Thompson, Peter E., 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Throckmorton, Lynn H., 1970; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Tigerstedt, P. M. A., 1974-1975; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Tilley, Robert J., 1972-1975; 9 items (Box 14)
  - Time Magazine, 1967; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Timoffeef-Ressovsky, Nikolai W., 1969-1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Tobach, Ethel, 1973-1975; 7 items (Box 14)
  - Tobias, Phillip V., 1972-1975; 10 items (Box 14)
  - Tollefson, Bruce E, 1972; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Tombaugh, Richard, 1961; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Tonelli, Livia, 1970; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Topping, Milton S., 1972; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Tordoff, Harrison B., 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Towers, Bernard, 1968-1972; 7 items (Box 14)
  - Towle, Patricia G., 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Tracey, Martin L., 1971-1974; 5 items (Box 14)
  - Travis, Janet L., 1970-1972; 7 items (Box 14)
  - Truesdell, C., 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Tschernezky, W., 1969; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Tsekeris, Pericles, 1973; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Turner, B. L., 1970-1972; 4 items (Box 14)
  - Turner, Perry Edward, Jr., 1971; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Twitty, Victor C., 1961-1962; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Tyler, Ralph, 1962; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Ukranian Academy of Arts and Sciences (in the U.S, Inc.), 1961; 1 item (Box 14)
  - UNESCO, 1972; 7 items (Box 14)
  - U.S. Forest Service, 1934; 2 items (Box 14)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - U. S. International University, 1972; 2 items (Box 14)
  - University of California Extension, Davis, 1972; 1 item (Box 14)
  - University of California, Davis, Genetics Department, 1974-1975; 21 items (Box 14)
  - University of Chicago, 1959; 1 item (Box 14)
  - University of Helsinki, 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - University of Houston, 1971; 2 items (Box 14)
  - University of Minnesota, 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - University of Western Australia, 1975; 2 items (Box 14)
  - University of Wisconsin-Parkside, 1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Unknown, 1962-1975; 7 items (Box 14)
  - Urbanek, Adam, 1971-1974; 5 items (Box 14)
  - Uvarov, B. P., 1937; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Vaidya, V. G., 1972; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Valentine, James W., 1975; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Vance, B. Dwain, 1972; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Van Frank, Richard, 1974; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Van Gelder, Richard G., 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Vandel, A., 1969-1971; 3 items (Box 14)
  - Vandenberg, Steven G, 1974; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Varela, E. A., 1939; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Vargas, Luis Alberto, 1975; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Varley, George C., 1961-1970; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Vasiliev, Boris, 1930; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Vavilov, N. I., 1929-1931; 8 items (Box 14)
  - Vaz, Zeferino, 1970; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Venezuela. Universidad Central de, 1968; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Vernadsky, George, 1962; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Viking Press Inc., 1969-1971; 2 items (Box 14)
  - Villa Serbelloni, 1970-1971; 9 items (Box 14)
  - Vives, Miguel Garcia, 1975; 1 item (Box 14)
  - Voelker Robert A., 1969; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Volkart, E. H., 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Volkmann, Brigitte, 1975; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Vollmar, Philip M., 1969-1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Von Borstel, R. C., 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Von der Pahlen, Alejo, 1975; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Vorontsov, N. N., 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Vuilleumier, François, 1972; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Waddington, Conrad Hal, 1959-1974; 12 items (Box 15)
  - Wade, Alex N., 1970-1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Walker, Norma Ford, 1962; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Walker, Warren F., Jr., 1971-1974; 11 items (Box 15)
  - Walker and Company, 1970; 4 items (Box 15)
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1971-1975; 3 folders (Box 15)
    Crick, Francis H. C.; Drosophila genetics; National Academy of Sciences; Political issues; Radiation genetics
    - Folder 1, 1972-1975; 13 items (Box 15)
    - Folder 2, 1972; 5 items (Box 15)
    - Folder 3, 1971; 9 items (Box 15)
  - Wanjoh, Gerald J., 1970-1974; 7 items (Box 15)
  - Ward, Richard H., 1975; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Warder, Michael Young, 1974-1975; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Waring, H., 1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Washburn, Sherwood L., 1962-1971; 5 items (Box 15)
  - Wasserman Marvin, 1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Weaver, John, 1972; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Weinstein, Paul R., 1970; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Weisbrot, David, 1971-1975; 11 items (Box 15)
    Biographical and personal data; Political issues -- Israel; Population genetics
  - Weiss, Wolkmar, 1968-1969; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Welch, Bruce L., 1972; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Wellesley-Wesley, James, 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, 1968-1971; 5 items (Box 15)
  - Went, F. W., 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Went, L. N., 1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wermstrom, Martha, 1938i; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Werner, Henry James, 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wesner, Gordon E., 1973; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Westergaard, Charles, 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wettstein, Fr. V., 1936-1938; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Whaley, W. Gordon E., 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wheeler, Harvey, 1973; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Wheeler, John Archibald, 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Whelan, Sidney S., Jr., 1971; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Whitaker, Douglas, 1970-1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - White, David C., 1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - White, Michael J. D., 1961-1975; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Folder 1, 1961-1972; 20 items (Box 15)
    - Folder 2, 1975; 3 items (Box 15)
    - Folder 3, n.d.; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Whitson, Gary L., 1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Whittinghill, Maurice, 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wickett, R. M., 1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wiley, Haven, Jr., 1970; 12 items (Box 15)
  - Wiley, John, and Sons, Inc., 1957-1971; 11 items (Box 15)
  - Wiley-Interscience, 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Williams, Curtis A., 1973-1974; 4 items (Box 15)
  - Williams, James S., 1971-1975; 9 items (Box 15)
  - Williams, Mary B., 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Willie, Charles V., 1974; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wills, Christopher, 1970-1973; 9 items (Box 15)
  - Wilson, E. O., 1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wilson, Katherine S., 1974; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wilson, Kent H., 1973; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wimsatt, William C., 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wispe, Lauren G., 1974-1975; 4 items (Box 15)
  - Wistrand, Harry, 1974-1975; 6 items (Box 15)
  - Witkin, Ewlyn M, 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wittenberg University, 1970; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Wojciechowski, Jerry A., 1975; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wolf, Thomas M., 1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wolfson, Jane L., 1973-1974; 4 items (Box 15)
  - Wolverton, Robert E., 1974; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Woodford, F. Peter, 1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1969-1970; 4 items (Box 15)
  - Woodward, Herbert N., 1972; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Woolf, Charles M., 1969-1975; 14 items (Box 15)
  - World Council of Churches, 1972; 6 items (Box 15)
  - World Health Organization, 1970-1974; 9 items (Box 15)
  - World Society for Ekistics, 1972; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Worth Publishers Inc., 1973; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Wright, L. H., 1971; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Wright, Sewall, 1973-1975; 6 items (Box 15)
  - Wright, Theodore R. F., 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Yablokov, Alexey V., 1971-1975; 6 items (Box 15)
  - Yale University, 1966-1971; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Yale University Press, 1969-1974; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Yamazaki, Tsuneyuki, 1970; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Yolton, John W., 1973; 6 items (Box 15)
  - Young, James R., Jr., 1972-1973; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Zähner, H., 1973; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Zavadskii, Killil Mikhailovich, 1973-1974; 3 item (Box 15)
  - Zavadovskii, B., 1930; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Zelenzov, N., 1971; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Zelinsky, P., 1930; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Zimmerman, Elwood C., 1972; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Zinn, Grover A., Jr., 1971; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Zirkle, Conway, 1962; 3 items (Box 15)
  - Zucchi, Ronaldo, 1970; 2 items (Box 15)
  - Zuckerkandl, Emile, 1972-1974; 8 items (Box 15)
  - Zwart, Bob, 1973; 1 item (Box 15)
  - Zygon Journal of Religion and Science, 1970-1975; 8 items (Box 15)
- Series II: Correspondence with Ernst Mayr, 1937-1975; B D65m; 0.25 linear feet
  Revealing correspondence between Dobzhansky and the evolutionary biologist, Ernst Mayr, regarding speciation, evolutionary theory, and genetics.
  Permission to quote from Series II must be obtained in advance from Ernst Mayr.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1975 (Box 1)
- Series III: Research notebooks, ca.1917-1974; 54 volumes; 1.0 linear feet
  The fifty-four notebooks and diaries give a virtually uninterrupted first-hand commentary on Dobzhansky's life and career, save for the period 1936-1941. Although the earliest dates are 1934, the first entries (sketches and data on coccinellid beetles) may have been made as early as 1917. With few exceptions, the entries are all in Russian, although two long stretches written in English occur during the late 1940s and early 1950s (presumably the years during which he felt most alienated from Russia) and from 1971 until his death. In an entry from this period, he commented that he was again writing in English so that his last thoughts would be accessible to friends and relatives unable to read Russian.
  Throughout the notebooks, Dobzhansky included extracts or copies of personal letters to or from family members and close friends. These record details of Dobzhansky's day-to-day life often lacking in his professional correspondence, and serve to round out the picture of his personality. These preserved items become increasingly numerous as he became older, particularly after the death of his wife in 1968. Among the manuscripts in the collection are 46 essays Dobzhansky wrote about his travels and sent home to his friends. He was often urged to publish these in collected form, but failed to do so. Excerpts from one appeared in 1970; but they were not published in their entirety until edited by Bentley Glass in 1985.
  Biographical and personal data; Honors; Russian politics and science; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Coccinellid data, ca.1920 (Box 1)
  - Coccinellid data, ca.1920 (Box 1)
  - Notes (I), 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes (II), 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes (III), 1935 (Box 1)
  - Notes (IV), 1935 (Box 1)
  - Notes (V), 1935 (Box 1)
  - Notes (II), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Notes (III), 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Notes (Black cover), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Notes (Brown cover), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Notes (1), 1949 (Box 1)
  - Notes (2) Brazil, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Notes (3), 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Notes (black cover), 1951 (Box 1)
  - Notes (brown cover), 1951 (Box 1)
  - Notes (1), 1952 (Box 1)
  - Notes (2), 1952 (Box 1)
  - Notes: Brazil-Texas, Sep. 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Notes: Flies received, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1955-1957 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Notes, June 1964-Sep. 1965 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Notes: Experimental data, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Notes, Sept. 1965-June 1966 (Box 2)
  - Notes, June 1966-Oct. 1969 (Box 2)
  - Notes, Jan. 1967-Aug. 1968 (Box 2)
  - Notes, Aug. 1968-Feb. 1969 (Box 2)
  - Notes, Mar. 1969-Aug. 1970 (Box 2)
  - Notes: Travelogue, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Notes, Oct. 1969-Sep. 1971 (Box 2)
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius. Passports (4), 1952, 1959, 1964, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Dobzhansky, Natalia. Passports (2), 1959, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Pocket diary, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Pocket diary, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Pocket diary, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Pocket diary, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1970-Mar. 1973 (Box 3)
  - Notes, Feb. 1971-Oct. 1971 (Box 3)
  - Notes, Oct. 1971-Aug. 1972 (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1972 Mar.-1973 Nov. (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1972 Aug.-1973 Feb. (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1973 Nov.-1974 June (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1974 June-1974 Nov. (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1974 Dec. (Box 3)
- Series IV: Human Culture (manuscript), 0.25 linear feet
  Manuscript of Dobzhansky's Human Culture: A Moment in Evolution (N.Y.: Columbia, 1983), with proofreader's notations.
  - Human Culture (manuscript), 1 vol. (Volume 1)
- Series V: Papers dedicated to Dobzhansky, 1970; 2 vols., 0.25 linear feet
  Two bound volumes of published articles dedicated (and usually inscribed) to Dobzhansky on the occasion of his 70th birthday in 1970, written by colleagues, former students, and friends.
  - Authors Ayala-Hoenigsberg, 1969-1970 (Volume 1)
  - Authors Kalmus-Zucchi, 1969-1970 (Volume 2)
- Series VI: Reminiscences, 1962; 2 vols., 0.25 linear feet
  With the paucity of material from early in Dobzhansky's life, the Reminiscences assume a considerable importance for documenting the early parts of his career and, apart from some materials in Russia, are the only source for his life prior to emigration.
  The two volumes of "Reminiscences," transcripts from the Columbia Oral History Project interviews conducted by Barbara Land in 1962, give a remarkably coherent and self-conscious picture of Dobzhansky's life. Encompassing descriptions of his childhood and student years in Russia, candid and anecdotal accounts of the people he had known throughout his career, and the places where he had worked and the experiments he had done, the reminiscences also include thoughts on various historical and political issues. Dobzhansky annotated them between 1962-1975, supplying names and dates as he remembered them, and adding information about his family background. The final notes are dated December 17, 1975, the day of his death.
  - Columbia Oral History interview, part 1, 1962 (Volume 1)
  - Columbia Oral History interview, part 2, 1962 (Volume 2)
- Series VII: Journal, 1926; B D65j; 0.25 linear feet
  Journal, in Russian, kept during the year prior to Dobzhansky's departure from the Soviet Union.
  Due to the fragility of the original, photocopy must be used.
  - Journal (in Russian), 1926 (Volume 1)
- Series VIII: Awards and memorabilia, 1935-1975; 1.0 linear feet
  A miscellaneous collection of awards and memorabilia, including major awards such as the Kimber Award in Genetics, the National Medal of Science, and the Daniel Elliot Giraud Medal.
  - Plaque: American Institute of Biological Sciences Distinguished Service Award, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Plaque: Benjamin Minge Duggar Lecturer, Auburn University, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Plaque: Council of the Society for the Study of Evolution, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Medal: Addison Emery Verrill Medal, Peabody Museum, Yale, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Medal: American Museum of Natural History, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Chancellerie des Universités de Paris, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Columbia University Bicentennial commemorative, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Daniel Giraud Elliot Award, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Deutsche Akademie der Naturfoscher Leopoldina, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Helsingienensis Universitas (Box 2)
  - Medal: Jardin du Roy, Paris, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Kimber Genetics Award, National Academy of Sciences, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Medal: National Academy of Sciences, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Medal: National Medal of Science, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Societé Zoologique de France (Box 2)
  - Medal: St. Louis University, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Umberto d'Ancona commemorative, ca.1967 (Box 2)
  - Medal: Université de Rennes, 1974 (Box 2)
- Series IX: Photographs, ca.1929-1974; 1.5 linear feet
  A mixture of candid photographs of Dobzhansky, his wife Natasha, and their friends, and photographs taken during field excursions and at meetings from throughout his career. Includes some formal portraits of Dobzhansky at various stages of life.
  - Dobzhansky sitting at desk with microscope., ca. 1959; 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length view of Dobzhansky sitting in laborator, 3/4 turn toward camera.
  - Dobzhansky portrait, informal., ca. 1970; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view, informal portrait of Dobzhansky, color photograph.
  - Walter Bodmer and Richard Lewontin, December 1965, Informal, color photograph of Lewontin and Bodmer seated at a conference.
  - Dobzhansky at his desk., 1965; Informal, color photograph of Dobzhansky seated at his desk with a large stack of papers before him.
  - Theodosius Dobzhansky., ca. 1966
  - Dobzhansky in his first car., ca. 1935
  - Theodosius Dobzhansky., ca. 1935
  - Dobzhansky camping., ca. 1940
  - Dobzhansky in a lab., Informal, black and white photograph of Dobzhansky seated in a lab with an unidentified man.
  - Theodosius and Natalia (Natasha) Sivertsev Dobzhansky.
  - Dobzhansky in lab with fly jars and assistant., 1959
  - Dobzhansky relaxing in director's chair., 1965
  - Dobzhansky collecting flies in Brazil., 1965
  - Dobzhansky and his "Fly maze.", 1965; Informal, black and white photograph of Dobzhansky standing in the laboratory and working on his "fly maze."
  - Theodosius Dobzhansky and Bruno Battaglia in Pomposa, Italy., Informal, black and white photograph of Dobzhansky and Battaglia standing outdoors before a religious icon on a brick building.
  - Calvin Bridges taking notes., n. d.; Informal, black and white photograph of Calvin Bridges seated with pen and paper.
  - Hampton Carson, Bruce Wallace, Theodosius Dobzhansky (r. to l.) at Cold Spring Harbor., 1959; Informal, black and white photograph of the three men seated outdoors.
  - Howard Levene., 1965; Informal, color photograph of Levene standing before a blackboard.
  - Thomas Hunt Morgan., n. d.; Formal, black and white photograph, autographed by Morgan.
  - Helen Redfield at Woods Hole, Mass. Marine Biological Laboratory., 1928; Informal, black and white photograph of Redfield before an array of bottles.
  - Jack Schultz at Woods Hole, Mass. Marine Biological Laboratory., 1928
  - Alfred Sturtevant relaxing in the grass., n. d.; Informal, black and white photograph of Sturtevant reclined on a grassy hill smoking a pipe.
  - N. W. Timofeeff-Ressovsky., 1966; Informal, black and white photograph, close-up of Timofeeff-Ressovsky smoking a cigarette.